# Guillermo Ortiz-Jiménez



in es.linkedin.com/in/gortizji/en

gortizji



gortizji.github.io





## About me

I am a **PhD student at EPFL** working under the supervision of Prof. Pascal Frossard. My current research focuses on **understanding deep learning** by studying the complex interactions between datasets, architectures and optimization. In my work, I am providing a novel framework to design better and **more reliable neural networks** that exploit prior knowledge about the world.

#### **Education**

Nov 2018 - (Spring 2023) PhD. Machine Learning

Ecole Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne, EPFL (Switzerland)

Sep 2016 - Aug 2018 MSc. Electrical Engineering (Best graduate)

Delft University of Technology, TU Delft (Netherlands)

Sep 2011 - Jun 2015 BSc. Telecommunications Engineering (Best graduate)

Universidad Politécnica de Madrid, UPM (Spain)

# Research experience

#### **Doctoral assistant** at EPFL

Nov 2018 - (Spring 2023) Lausanne, Switzerland

Studying the **inductive bias** of deep learning and how it affects its generalization and robustness properties. My research has already provided insights to improve **out-of-distribution generalization**, **adversarial defenses**, and to understand the **role of architecture in deep learning**.

#### Master thesis at TU Delft.

Nov 2017 - Aug 2018 Delft, Netherlands

Introduced a novel algorithm based on submodular optimization to sample tensor data and reconstruct it with near-optimal guarantees. Applications to point cloud compression and recommender systems.

## Research Intern at Philips Healthcare Research

Jul 2017 - Oct 2017 Hamburg, Germany

Developed self-supervised deep learning algorithms for representation learning and medical image reconstruction of fetal ultrasounds and CT scans.

#### Research Assistant at Universidad Politécnica de Madrid

Jul 2015 - Jul 2016 Madrid, Spain

Pioneered the use of 3D rendering techniques from computer graphics to simulate radar scattering from the human skin at the THz band.

## Software skills

**DL frameworks:** JAX, PyTorch, Tensorflow **Languages:** Python, C, Matlab, Javascript, Java

Misc: Unix, git, docker, vim

## Languages

Spanish:••••English:••••German:••••French:••••

**Dutch:** • • • • •

## **Awards**

2018 National Award for Excellence in Academic Performance by Government of Spain

2018 Best graduate by TU Delft (~1000 students)

2016 "La Caixa" Postgraduate Fellowship by La Caixa Foundation (~45,000\$)

2015 Best graduate by Universidad Politecnica de Madrid (~800 students)

Other competitive grants (~18,000\$)

# **Featured publications**

#### **ML Conferences**

- What can linearized neural networks actually say about generalization?. GOJ, S.M. Moosavi-Dezfooli and P. Frossard. In *Advances of Neural Information Processing Systems*, NeurIPS 2021.
- **Neural Anisotropy Directions.** GOJ\*, A. Modas\*, S.M. Moosavi-Dezfooli and P. Frossard. In *Advances of Neural Information Processing Systems*, NeurIPS 2020.
- Hold me tight! Influence of discriminative features on deep network boundaries. GOJ\*, A. Modas\*, S.M. Moosavi-Dezfooli and P. Frossard. In *Advances of Neural Information Processing Systems*, NeurIPS 2020.

#### **Journals**

- Optimism in the face of adversity: Understanding and improving deep learning through adversarial robustness. GOJ, A. Modas, S.M. Moosavi-Dezfooli and P. Frossard. *Proceedings of the IEEE*. Feb 2021
- Sparse sampling for inverse problems with tensors. GOJ, M. Coutino, S.P. Chepuri and G. Leus. *IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing*, Jun 2019

#### **ML Workshops**

- A neural anisotropic view of underspecification in deep learning. GOJ, I.F. Salazar-Reque, A. Modas, S.M. Moosavi-Dezfooli and P. Frossard. In *RobustML Workshop (ICLRw 2021)*
- Redundant features can hurt robustness to distribution shifts. GOJ\*, A. Modas\*, S.M. Moosavi-Dezfooli and P. Frossard. In *Uncertainty & Robustness in Deep Learning Workshop (ICMLw 2020)*

#### **Others**

- On the choice of graph neural network architectures. C. Vignac, GOJ, and P. Frossard. In IEEE Conference on Audio and Signal Processing, ICASSP 2020
- Forward-backward splitting for optimal transport based problems. GOJ, M. El Gheche, E. Simou and P. Frossard. In *IEEE Conference on Audio and Signal Processing*, ICASSP 2020

# **Teaching experience**

- Machine learning.
- Fundamentals of inference and learning.
- A network tour of data science.
- Computational optimal transport.

# **Community service**

Reviewer in NeurIPS, ICLR, ICCV, IEEE TPAMI, ...

## **Personal interests**

Climbing, running, hiking, skiing, cooking and photography.